Finding Aid for Emmett N. Leith papers, 1954-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Emmett N. Leith papers 1954-2005
Leith, Emmett N.
12 linear feet
00105 Aa 2
Emmett Leith (1927 - 2005), former Professor of Engineering at the University of Michigan, is known as one of the fathers of holography for his advances in 1963 that made the industry possible. He was a well-regarded teacher. The Leith papers span his entire professional career and include background information, articles, teaching and presentation materials, topical and chronological research files (notes, reports, and illustrations).
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The first accession came from the Emmett Leith in June 2000 (Donor # 8969 ). The second accession came from the University of Michigan Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science in August 2006.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research.
Emmett Leith was born in Detroit, Michigan on March 12th, 1927. He received his bachelors (1950) and masters (1952) in physics from Wayne State University before beginning work as a Research Associate at the University of Michigan-affiliated Willow Run Laboratories in 1954. Through his research on side-along-radar (SAR) and with the assistance of Juris Upatnieks he was able to revive the long forgotten field of holography. Holography was originally developed by Dennis Gabor in 1947. However Gabor's process was hindered by a twin image and his research was eventually abandoned. In 1963 Leith and Upatnieks where able to eliminate the twin image and, with the assistance of the newly available laser, able to create stunning three dimensional images.
Leith continued to research in the field of holography and eventually focused much of his time on applying holography to imaging through biological tissue. Leith was a prolific writer who wrote for a variety of journals. In addition to his research in holography Leith became a spokesman for the field and was often asked to speak and write on the field of holography as a whole in addition to his own work.
Leith became an Associate Professor of Electrical Engineering in 1963, a full professor in 1966, and the Schlumberger Professor of Engineering in 1981. He was well regarded by his students as an excellent teacher with a profound love for the subjects he taught and dedication to his students. Leith died on December 23, 2005, at the age of 78, just before his retirement was to become effective at the end of the year.
The Bentley Historical Library received the materials in this collection through two accessions. The first came from Emmett Leith himself in 2000. The second came from the University of Michigan, Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science in 2006. The collection is comprised of five series: Background; Articles, 1959-2006; Teaching, 1966-2004; Research; and George Stroke. The materials were received with very little apparent order. Consequently, the series and subseries are artificial with the exception of the Articles Series which, for the most part, was well organized.
Subjects:
Leith, Emmett N.; Holography.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Holography.; Leith, Emmett N.; Teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Photographs.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Background
  The Background series (1 linear foot) contains materials that are descriptive of Leith and his career, including his CV. Notable in the series is a scrapbook containing newspaper articles in which Leith is mentioned. Many of the articles were printed around the time when Leith's advances in holography were becoming known to the public. This series contains photographs of Leith with various individuals, including some of Leith early in his career. Also included in this series is a recount by Upatnieks of his work with Leith in holography.
  - Vita and Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - "Development of Holography: from November 1962 to January 1965" by Juris Upatnieks 1965 (Box 1)
  - Newsclippings and Articles about Leith, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
- Articles 1959-2006
  Articles, 1959 - 2006 (2.3 linear feet) consists of four files of Leith's own writings. The first three files were arranged and named by Leith. The first, Radar Lab - Reprints, is named after the research group he worked in at Willow Run laboratories. Much of his work at this time was not published due to classification and so is not represented in this file. This was the time period when Leith and Upatnieks made their first major discoveries in holography. The second file, Technical Papers, 1971 - 2006 contains the bulk of his intellectual output. Leith divided this collection of papers into four volumes. Each of these volumes begins with a hand written contents list that numbers all the articles in that volume with their title and primary contributors. The Non Technical Papers, 1959-1990 has no further divisions and does not include a written contents list. The articles in this file are written for a wide range of expertise. Some are "popular" articles for the general public and others are very technical articles written for those with an engineering background who may not have much knowledge of optics or holography. The Miscellaneous file consists of unsorted articles and essays which Leith had not included in either of the other three categories. Many of them do not seem to have been published and some were probably written as texts for his students. Also included in this series is a List of Publications, June 5, 1984 compiled by Leith, although it is not comprehensive.
  - List of Publications June 5, 1984 (Box 2)
    (incomplete)
  - Radar Lab-Reprints 1959-1966, 25 folders
    - Folders 1-25 (Box 2)
  - Technical Papers 1971-2006
    - Vol. 1 1971-1980, 53 folders (Box 2)
    - Vol. 2 1980-1989, 49 folders (Box 2)
    - Vol. 3 1989-1996, 53 folders (Box 2)
    - Vol. 4 1996-2006, 41 folders (Box 3)
  - Non Technical Papers 1959-1990, 47 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 64 folders
    - Folders 1-38 (Box 3)
    - Folders 39-64 (Box 4)
- Research 1954-2005
  Research, 1954-2005 (5 linear feet) is divided into two subseries: Topical and Chronological. Topical file folders were often named by Leith after a research project, a colleague or advisee, a paper, or an event and are arranged alphabetically. There is little consistency about what forms of material are housed within a given topical file. They are often combinations of hand written notes, drafts or reprints of his own or other's articles, reports, drawings, holograms, transparencies, and correspondence. Some files are much larger than the rest. Two large files are the "Navy Reports" file (projects sponsored by the Navy specifically) and the "ARO - AF" file (projects primarily sponsored by the Army Research Office) and consist mainly of reports written for the respective units. The final file in the subseries contains a run of correspondence from when Leith worked at the Willow Run Laboratories. Another folder of note, "Images," contains a variety of images including viewgraphs and hologram transparencies. The Chronological subseries consists mostly of planning and group meeting notes with no distinct project association but was kept chronologically, often with a running page enumeration.
  - Topical
    - 3-D Images Transmitted through Single-Mode Fibers Using Monochromatic Light 1995 (Box 4)
    - 3-D Imaging with Parallel Pixel Filtering Techniques January 1993-September 1993 (Box 4)
    - Achromatic Fringe Work circa 1965 (Box 4)
    - [Achromatic Fringe] A.F. Hologram Work circa 1965 (Box 4)
    - Achromatic Interferometry Using Holographic Optical Elements NSF Grant ECS-7901647) July 1979-August 1980 (Box 4)
    - Americana 1968 (Box 4)
    - ARO (Army Research Office)-AF 1981-2001, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Beste, D. circa 1954-1972 (Box 4)
    - [Best, D.C. and E. N. Leith, "An Optical Technique for Simultaneous Beamforming and Cross-Correlation"] undated (ca. 1954-1972) (Box 4)
    - Canada World Fair circa 1954-1972 (Box 4)
    - Center for Opto-Electronic Information Processing 1 November 1988-31 October 1993 (Box 4)
    - C. Chen circa 1990, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Ye Chen circa 1991 (Box 5)
    - Chirp Confocal Paper undated (Box 5)
    - Chirp Confocal and Technology Transfer 2004 (Box 5)
    - Coherent Light Investigation, Volume III, AF33(615)-1014 October 1964 (Box 5)
    - Coherence Methods for Imaging into Volume Media undated (Box 5)
    - A Communication Theory of Reconstructed Wavefronts April 10, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Complex Filter circa 1954-1972 (Box 5)
    - Confocal imaging into scattering media with femtosecond pulses 1990-1993 (Box 5)
    - Confocal October 2001 onward (Box 5)
    - Confocal III circa April 2002 (Box 5)
    - Confocal and SAR circa 1999 (Box 5)
    - Continuous Tones circa 1963 (Box 5)
    - Critique of a System for Transmission of 3-D Images circa 1965-1969 (Box 5)
    - A Data Processing System Viewed as an Optical Model of a Radar System May 22, 1956 (Box 5)
    - Diffractive Structures in Optical Communication Systems November 1, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Electronic Holography with Incoherent Light for Imaging through Scattering Media 1 June 1993-31 May 1996 (Box 5)
    - Emmett Leith's Report, "Photographic Film as an Element of a Coherent Optical System," 1961 (Box 5)
    - Fly's-Eye Lens Model for Evaluating Image Quality of the Scatter-Plate Imaging Process February 13, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Gabor circa 1954-1972 (Box 5)
    - Gabor Correspondence 1968-1972 (Box 5)
    - Hologram Scaling by Imagery August 29, 1966 (Box 5)
    - The Hologram Technique and Potential Applications (AF (18) 600-2779) June 1965 (Box 5)
    - Hologram Visual Displays, Imagery Thru Diffuse Materials, Holograms: Their Properties and Uses 1965 (Box 5)
    - Holographic optical elements March 1978-October 1986, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Holographic Optical Elements Formed in Light of Reduced Coherence, 1 December 1984-9 March 1988 (Box 5)
    - Images (prints) undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Imaging through Fibers, Phase 2 (F30602-94-C-0059) May 1995-November 1996 (Box 6)
    - Imaging Through Tissue circa 1996 (Box 6)
    - Information Processing with Incoherent Light 1 October 1986-31 March, 1991 (Box 6)
    - Information Sciences Paper circa October 2002 (Box 6)
    - Integral Photo and Multiplex circa 1984 (Box 6)
    - Interferometric Methods Applied to Multichannel Optical Waveguide Technology October 1973 (Box 6)
    - Investigation of Coherent Imaging Systems, March 1971-19 June 1974 (Box 6)
    - Investigation of Coherent Optics to the BMD Problem (DASG-60-77-C-0082) 15 April 1977-15 August 1980, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Investigation of Generalized Lenses 15 December 1973-14 December 1975, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Investigation of Generalized Lenses April 1, 1977 (Box 6)
    - Investigation of Hologram Techniques, (AF 18(600)-2779 AF 33(615)-1014 AF 33(615)-1593) January 1965 (Box 6)
    - Investigation of Hologram Techniques (AF 33(615)-3100) July 1965-June 1968 (Box 7)
    - Investigation of Hologram Techniques (F33615-68-1310) 1 February 1970-29 February 1972, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Investigation of Holographic Testing Techniques (DAAG46-69-C-0017) 27 November 1968-28 July 1971 (Box 7)
    - Investigation of Image Formation in Scattering and Other Irregular Media 1 July 2000-30 June 2003 (Box 7)
    - Investigation of Interferometric Waveguides 1 April 1974-31 March 1977 (Box 7)
    - Investigation of Super Resolution by Incoherent to Coherent Conversion 1 March 1988-29 May 1990 (Box 7)
    - JOSA 3-D Paper circa 1964, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Lens Aberration Correction 1965 (Box 7)
    - Massey, N. 1963 (Box 7)
    - Microscopy 1965 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous 1961-1965 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1972-1989 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Foreign Requests circa 1954-1972 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Papers in Progress & Book circa 1954-1972 (Box 7)
    - Multiperspective Autostereoscopic Imagers and Viewer (MAIV) b(A03201013) undated (Box 7)
    - NASA, undated circa 1954-1972 (Box 7)
    - Navy Reports August 1969-February 1970 (Box 7)
    - New Methods for Imaging Into and Through Inhomogeneous Media 1 June 1990-31 May 1993 (Box 7)
    - Optical Processing Techniques, Final Technical Report (AF33(615)-3388) December 1966 (Box 7)
    - Papers to be Given circa 1954-1972 (Box 7)
    - Phase Shift Codes 1964 (Box 7)
    - Photography Materials September 13, 1965 (Box 7)
      (Correspondence with Kodak)
    - Popular Papers 1965 (Box 7)
    - Proposal for Investigation of the Application of Near Image Plane Holography to Microelectronics November 22, 1968 (Box 7)
    - Proposal for the Investigation of Hologram Techniques February 10, 1969 (Box 7)
    - [Proposal for the Investigation of Hologram Techniques for Aerospace Applications] undated (Box 7)
    - A Proposal for the Use of Interferometry as an Aid for Imaging Through Scattering Media (post 1972 (Box 8)
    - Proposed Method for Visible Light Display of Electromagnetically Obtained "Images" By New Principles of Wave-Front Reconstruction Techniques December 1963 (Box 8)
    - Pseudo-Random Diffusers for Coherent Illumination (AF 33(615)15-68-C-1310) July 1968 (Box 8)
    - Radar Data Processing Techniques (F33 615-67-C-1814) August 1976 (Box 8)
    - Radar Papers, Unclassified 1965 (Box 8)
    - Range Curvature circa 1969-1972 (Box 8)
    - Report of E. Leith on STC October 20, 1994 (Box 8)
    - Rotz, F. 1962-1965 (Box 8)
    - Signal Film Simulation Program for One Year July 18, 1963 (Box 8)
    - Some Thoughts on Redundancy and Reduction of Coherent Optical System Noise November 12, 1969 (Box 8)
    - SMP& E ["Requirements for a Wavefront Reconstruction Television Facsimile System"] 1965 (Box 8)
    - SPIE Papers circa 1954-1972 (Box 8)
    - A Study of Hologram Recording and Applications July 1970 (Box 8)
    - Sun Project circa 1990 (Box 8)
    - Super Resolution for Imaging through Inhomogeneities and Small Apertures 11 April 1990-30 September 1993 (Box 8)
    - Synthetic Aperture Systems for All-Range Focusing, Range Curvature Correction, and Tracking Using the Chirp Balancing Method June 14, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Talks, Summaries, etc. circa 1954-1972 (Box 8)
    - Thank You's-Colleagues circa 1954-1972 (Box 8)
    - TW Product of Lenses 1960 (Box 8)
    - Volume Diffraction Processes June 1, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Vossler 1992 (Box 8)
    - Wavefront Reconstruction Disclosure April 22, 1964 (Box 8)
    - WESCON (Western Electronic Show and Convention) 1963-1964 (Box 8)
    - White Light Optical Information Processing (AFOSR 81 0243) 9 March 1977-31 December 1984, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Willow Run Correspondence 1955-1966, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Chronological
    - Research Notes 1960-1962 (Box 8)
    - [Computation Book] 10 March 1965-16 November 1981 (Box 8)
    - [Notebook] 13 October 1978-6 February 1992 (Box 9)
    - Research Notes 1989-2005
      - 1989-1996 (Box 9)
      - April 1992-June 2005 (Box 9)
      - circa May 1999 (Box 9)
      - 1999-2005 (Box 9)
      - circa February 2002 (Box 9)
      - circa Summer 2003 (Box 9)
- Teaching 1966-2004
  Teaching, 1966-2004 (2.5 linear feet) comprises samples of material documenting Leith as a professor and mentor to students and an instructor of professionals. The ECE 575 / EECS 535: Optical Information Processing subseries (the course number changed from ECE 575 to EECS 535 around 1985) serves to document the materials Leith used in the instruction of upper level university students. It was chosen for retention due to its comprehensiveness compared to other available teaching materials. Notably absent, however, are the visual aids Leith often used in teaching (although they were often reproduced in the "course notes"). Continuing Education (Summer Short Courses) subseries documents some of Leith's instruction of professionals in the form of course notes, evaluations, and descriptions. The Presentations and Lectures subseries is a collection of texts, notes, or transcripts for some of the presentations given by Leith in a variety of venues. The Thesis and Dissertation Acknowledgements are photocopies Leith kept in his office of the title page and acknowledgement sections of thesis and dissertations in which he is mentioned by name in the acknowledgement.
  - ECE 575 / EECS 535: Optical Information Processing
    - 575 [and 535] Problem Sets (Box 9)
    - 575 Notes January 1978 (Box 9)
    - 757 as Given in Winter 1993 (Box 9)
    - 535 Notes, Masters: 1995, 1998, 2000 (Box 9)
    - 535 All Tests (Box 9)
    - 535 Notes 1991 (Box 9)
    - 535-1989 (Box 9)
    - 535 Lecture Notes (Box 9)
    - Tests 1969-1982 (Box 10)
    - 535 Miscellaneous 1995 (Box 10)
    - [Loose Material inside binder] 1995-2002 (Box 10)
    - 535 Binder (Box 10)
      (moved into a folder)
    - [Loose Material] (Box 10)
    - Optics, Book 1 (Box 10)
    - Optical Data Process[ing], Part II 1966 (Box 10)
  - Continuing Education (Summer Short Courses)
    - Short Course Notes
      - "Introduction to Optical Data-Processing" Summer Engineering Conference, Course Notes 1966 (Box 10)
      - SPIE Tutorial T9 "Fundamentals of Modern Holography," April 18, 1983 (Box 10)
      - SPIE SC72 "Fundamentals of Modern Holography," July 10, 1990 (Box 10)
      - SPIE SC397 "Holographic Methods for Imaging into Volume Media," August 1, 2001 (Box 10)
    - SPIE Short Course Evaluations 1983, 1985 (Box 10)
    - Introduction to Optical Processing (Class Schedule) 25 July 1966-5 August 1966 (Box 10)
    - Fundaments and Applications of Optical Data Processing and Holography (Brochure) July, 1970 (Box 10)
    - Principles of Imaging Radars (Brochure) July 1970 (Box 10)
    - Optical Processing: Fundamentals and Applications (Description and Brochure) July 1972 (Box 10)
  - Presentations and Lectures
    - Henry Russel Lecture 1982 (Box 11)
    - [Optics Education at Michigan] circa 1990 (Box 11)
    - "Some Highlights in the History of Information Optics," March 11-14, 2002 (Box 11)
      (Keynote Speech at the 1st Symposium on Photonics, Networking and Computing in conjunction with the 6th Joint Conference on Information Sciences)
    - "Holography in the United States, 1994" (Box 11)
      (1994 Gordon Conference)
    - Gordon Conference, Colorado 2004 (Box 11)
    - [Gordon Conference] Colorado 2004 General (Box 11)
    - [Gordon Conference] Colorado 2004 Specialized (Box 11)
    - "Coherence methods for unconventional imaging processes," October 19, 1998 (Box 11)
    - Coherence Imaging (Box 11)
    - Imaging Through Fiber circa 1995 (Box 11)
    - Supper resolution and Imaging through fiber (Box 11)
    - Imaging through tissue February 6, 1996 (Box 11)
      (Talk at Systems Div. Seminar)
    - Imaging through tissue 1995 (Box 11)
      (Used for ICASSP, Detroit)
    - Fourier Optics View of Photon Migration (Box 11)
    - Photon Migration 2 (Box 11)
    - Optical Sectioning as given in Finland (ICO Topical Meeting on Polarization Optics) 30 June 2003-3 July 2003 (Box 11)
    - Confocal as last given at CIOS on April 25, 2003 (Box 11)
    - Holography Confocal-Advanced (Box 11)
    - [Untitled Lecture] May 26-31, 1991 (Box 11)
      (International Conference on Signal Theory and Image Technology)
    - "Holographic Block-Oriented, Random-Access Memories-Problems and Prospects," July 18-20, 1978 (Box 11)
      (Presented at IGC Conference on Advances in Optical Information Storage)
    - "What is Holography," Spring 1968 (Box 11)
      (Lecture 1 in the University of California Extension, Statewide Lecture Series)
    - Fiber 2000 (Box 11)
    - Holography "A New Form of Photography," April 2, 1989, (VHS tape (Box 11)
      (Presented at the Loyola University of Chicago)
  - Thesis and Dissertation Acknowledgements
    - Photocopies (Box 11)
- George Stroke File
  The George Stroke, series (1 linear foot) was referred to by Leith as his "Stroke file." George Stroke was a colleague with whom relations were very strained in regards to claims about holographic research. Leith kept the file as a record of all his dealings with Stroke. The series consists primarily of correspondence with colleagues and copies of articles. The series has been left unprocessed.
  - Unprocessed Material (Box 12)